{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Which of the following is not used for detection in GC?", "opta": "Infrared spectroscopy", "optb": "NMR", "optc": "Flame ionisation", "optd": "Electrical conductivity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of these effects result from slow injection of a large sample volume?", "opta": "Increased resolution", "optb": "Decreased resolution", "optc": "Non-linear detector response", "optd": "Constant resolution", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The GC trace obtained after an experiment is called a", "opta": "chromatograph", "optb": "chromatogram", "optc": "chromatophore", "optd": "graph", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following detectors give concentration-dependent signals?", "opta": "Electron-capture detector", "optb": "Thermal conductivity", "optc": "Infra-red detector", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What useful information can be found from a Van Deemter plot?", "opta": "The selectivity factor", "optb": "Optimum mobile phase flow rate", "optc": "Optimum column temperature", "optd": "Optimum column length", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the typical internal diameter of fused silica capillary columns?", "opta": "0.2-0.3 mm", "optb": "0.3-0.5mm", "optc": "0.5-1.0 mm", "optd": "1.0-2.0 mm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Resolution is proportional to the", "opta": "number of theoretical plates in a column", "optb": "square root of the number of theoretical plates in a column", "optc": "square of the number of theoretical plates in a column", "optd": "cube root of the number of theoretical plates in a column", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Derivatisation of a sample is carried out to", "opta": "reduce polarity of the analytes", "optb": "increase the detector response", "optc": "increase volatility of the analytes", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the statements is correct?", "opta": "Gas chromatography is used to analyse gases", "optb": "Gas chromatography is used to analyse solids", "optc": "Gas chromatography is used to analyse gases, solutions and solids", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In column switching chromatography", "opta": "compounds trapped on one column are eluted to another column", "optb": "one column is removed and replaced by another", "optc": "the flow to the column is switched on and off repeatedly", "optd": "any of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A retention gap is placed between the injector and the front of the column to", "opta": "retain contaminants and prevent them from reaching the column", "optb": "retain the sample and release it gradually to the column", "optc": "prevent backflush of the injected solution", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following detectors give mass flow-dependent signals?", "opta": "Electron capture detector", "optb": "Field ionisation detector", "optc": "Thermal conductivity detector", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Headspace analysis is carried out in order to", "opta": "analyse volatile compounds from solid or liquid samples", "optb": "determine the psychological state of the tutor", "optc": "analyse the column contents ahead of the sample", "optd": "determine non-volatiles", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Split injection is carried out by", "opta": "splitting the sample into smaller portions to inject sequentially", "optb": "splitting the sample into smaller portions to inject at the same time through parallel ports", "optc": "splitting off some of the sample so that it does not enter the column", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What does the retention factor, k', describe?", "opta": "The distribution of an analyte between the stationary and the mobile phase", "optb": "The migration rate of an analyte through a column", "optc": "The velocity of the mobile phase", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Theoretical plates are used to", "opta": "estimate the efficiency of a column", "optb": "determine the thickness of the stationary phase", "optc": "measure the distribution of the analyte between mobile and stationary phases", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What does the selectivity factor describe?", "opta": "The proportional difference in widths of two chromatographic peaks", "optb": "The maximum number of different species which a column can separate simultaneously", "optc": "The relative separation achieved between two species", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Helium is generally preferred as carrier gas over nitrogen and hydrogen because", "opta": "it is inert", "optb": "it has a lower viscosity", "optc": "it doubles up as a party gas for balloons and funny voices", "optd": "all of above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The column is heated to", "opta": "prevent analyte condensation within the column", "optb": "control elution of the different analytes", "optc": "reduce band broadening to get sharper peaks", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What are the benefits of decreasing the column internal diameter?", "opta": "Increased sample capacity", "optb": "Increased resolution", "optc": "Reduced risk of column overloading", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sample retention in the column is measured by", "opta": "retention time", "optb": "retention factor", "optc": "retention index", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Column bleeding occurs when", "opta": "elution of the analyte is extended over time", "optb": "the column is cracked and stationary phase leaks out", "optc": "traces of the stationary phase are eluted", "optd": "the column breaks during installation and causes personal injury", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following are not used as stationary phases in a GC column?", "opta": "Polysiloxanes", "optb": "Silica", "optc": "Cyclodextrins", "optd": "None are used as stationary phases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Doubling the column's length increases resolution by a factor of", "opta": "(2)0.5", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sample injection is considered successful if", "opta": "all of the sample in the injector has been added to the column", "optb": "the sample is concentrated at the start of the column", "optc": "the sample is spread evenly along the column", "optd": "the sample is homogenously spread along the column", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following gases is unsuitable for use as a GC carrier gas?", "opta": "Nitrogen", "optb": "Helium", "optc": "Oxygen", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}